Oh, yeah.
It'll have to be one of the silver ones.
Okay. Very good. All right, everybody.
Good evening. I'm calling to order the
July 15, 2025 work session for uh city
council. Um
we will begin with the roll call of
members. Mr. Harris, if you would.
Yes, madam president. Mr. Matt
here.
Mr. Royo
Mr. Cle, Miss Craig
here.
Miss Diaz.
Mr. Hersh
here.
President Baker
here. Councelor K is excused this
evening. Uh we'll now move to the
approval of the minutes of our June
17th, 2025 work session meeting.
Motion to approve. Second.
We have a motion and a second for the
meeting minutes. Counselors, any
comments on them?
Hearing none. Mr. Harris, if you would.
Mr. Man,
I
Mr. Roya
I.
Miss Craig
Mr. H.
I.
President B. I thank you uh councilors.
This evening we have a a brief agenda uh
that involves discussing the
administration administrative code that
was presented at our June 17th meeting.
Public comment will be taken at the end
of that discussion. Um and I want to uh
just uh thank everyone for being patient
with the any audio issu issues. We're
working on uh temporary equipment that
uh is connected uh wirelessly to our
speakers in the room. there may be
interference in that and we will try to
work through that as best as we can. Um,
so I will now turn it over to Mr.
Henburgger who will lead our discussion.
Thank you. Thank you. So as a as a
reminder, what you have before you is
only about half of the admin code. The
other half will be presented to you in
August. Um this section deals mostly and
primarily with with uh financial policy
um and some other similar related
matters. Um I reviewed with you uh as we
went through the screen sort of the
general topics of uh the general
positions of all of the M materials that
are in what you've been presented to
date. Um I did receive two comments um
andor questions from uh counselors uh
and I'd just like to address both of
those. Um so we did receive one comment
about the um schedules for both the
capital budget and the budget and
changing the name of um budget activity
to due date or something similar to
that. Uh and we certainly will do that.
It was I don't have the specific
language. I believe you presented it Mr.
Earth. But um
yeah, it was just a comment about, you
know, I kind of thought and I racked my
brain as I looked at it again because I
was like, I'm not sure. I mean, maybe it
doesn't make much of a difference, but I
thought, you know, um having the budget
activity like the what on the far left,
then the due date, and then who's
responsible for it would just kind of
read better like like just the way it
reads now, it kind of
um like the date isn't as relevant to
people necessarily as like the what. And
so if you start with the what and then
say like so preparation of budget,
when's it due? It's due on before the
last meeting of council. and um the resp
the responsible parties. Um I mean I
might be splitting hairs so I just
No, when I looked when I looked at it
when it came in I thought it was a good
suggestion. I've actually already
implemented in draft format. So
I agree with you council hirs better
that way.
Um the second was really more a question
about interpretation of the charter
itself. Um the charter as it relates to
controller um sets forth the
qualifications for the controller
position. Um and there's a difference
between controller and deputy controller
and one is mandatory and obviously one
is not. Um so in the charter and I'm
just going to make sure I get you to the
right section.
Um
the controller is article 4 which starts
at page 20
and the prim I mean other than obviously
being a 21 and uh resident of the city
for at least one year the the primary
qualification is that you be a quote
accountant. Um this is a carryover. This
is the same provision that has existed
for decades and decades uh under
multiple versions of the third class
city code. Uh the word accountant is not
a defined term. Um in other words, that
doesn't mean you there's no there's no
law that says it has to be somebody who
is certified public accountant. Um they
they could be um uh it is really um
historically comes from the word
somebody who counts money. Uh so it is
open to interpretation as to what that
means. Uh the government study
commission determined to leave that to
the voters to determine whether a person
was qualified or not. That being said,
the controller has expanded
responsibilities and the government
study commission acknowledging that
thought that the controller may need
assistance technical and expertise uh
and if so has the ability to request and
appoint may appoint a deputy controller
in the instance that council approves
the appointment of a deputy controller.
The deputy controller has a has a
requirement of being a certified public
accountant. so that there is some
guarantee to the city that the
controller seeking additional expertise
is actually seeking that of a certified
public accountant which is a licensed
public accountant under Commonwealth of
Pennsylvania and other states as well.
So th those were the two comments and or
questions we received um in between last
month's meeting and this month. Um
tonight we are open to any discussion
regarding any of the other provisions
and there may not be any. you may be
satisfied with the drafts and to allow
more discussion to happen when this
comes up for vote. But if there are any
questions regarding the provisions or
any discussion about them, that's what
we're here to do tonight. Uh, and I'll
start by just asking, are there any?
Mr. Hamburger, um, I don't have any
specific questions at this moment, but
can you can we re reiterate where that
controller section is in the document? I
I'm looking at page 20 and I just don't
see it, so I want to make sure I'm
looking at the exact right spot.
Sure. And maybe my printing has paid
the PDF is different than the printed.
It's article 4.
Article 4.
Um, and the accountant language is in
section 4.03.
It's 4.03A.
Oh, I'm way
in the charter, not in the admin code.
Article four. Okay.
Maybe I'm not looking at the quite right
page, but
yeah, when I when I asked I'm sorry,
is it article five?
Yeah, when I asked the question,
I asked the question and I know I had
either the section wrong or the article
wrong.
Yeah, the elected controller under the
charter is article four.
Okay.
Of the charter itself.
The one I'm seeing article four is
salaries of elected officials. But
uh are you looking at
Are you looking at the admin code or the
charter?
I'm sorry. I'm looking at the admin
code.
Right. So the the charter it's article
4. This keep in mind remember tab.
Yeah. Remember remember and this is for
the public too. This is this is sort of
just to remember that the real Bible
is the charter. That's the part that we
can't change. It's already been done.
It's been approved by the electors of
the city of Lancaster. and you uh that
is that is sort of the law that we live
by.
Um so the charter has already determined
through the government study process
what the qualifications for the
controller are, what the job
responsibilities are.
Got it. Okay. I thank you for that. I
was I was looking at the wrong tab. Um I
appreciate that and I see where we're
looking and I don't I don't have
anything further in this uh section of
articles.
Maybe we could go around and just make
sure that everyone gets heard in case
there's anything else. And I'll I'll
just go around. Council Councilwoman
Craig.
I I don't have anything further.
Uh Councilman Royal.
Uh I actually don't have any questions
or comments. I thought um yeah, I
thought the changes that were suggested
during the last uh reading were very
valid and yeah, feel good about it.
Council H.
I just had one question. um section
three which is on page 25 of the admin
code um that's before us it talks about
the sale of personal property um
am I correct my understanding is that
the threshold for sale of personal
property as far as like resolution
approval by council is about $2500
and is that coming from state law
because I just didn't see that listed
here And um like is there just
superseding state law that governs that
or
No, there's no there's again what we
have was the old third class city code.
Third class city code talks about $2,000
in terms of
um then requiring a formal bid process.
Um under $2,000 would still need to be
approved by city council. So no matter
what the amount, disposal of city
property under the third class city code
would have to be approved by council. Um
the the the language here has been
written um and suggested in terms of the
personal property to allow operations to
proceed um efficiently and effectively
and also to make sure that the taxpayers
are protected.
But to be clear, those thresholds that
were affirmented, those are still in
place.
They're currently in place until the
admin code is adopted.
The admin code does not have any
thresholds on personal property.
So again, this is this is a draft for
your consideration. Um the the code if
you were to take in a threshold right
now, there are no thresholds for
requiring council approval. So if the
city of Lancaster wanted to dispose of a
uh a laptop,
theoretically, it would need council
approval.
Mhm. regardless of the condition of that
laptop.
Yeah. And I'm not saying I mean, you
know, maybe
I don't know what an appropriate
threshold is, but maybe that's something
we ought to
consider. Um,
well, again, I think that the different
language here is keep in mind that
council approval would be needed if the
property has use. So if it's determined
that it has no more use to the city in
this particular case, the way the
provision is drafted, then the director
of administrative services uh can
arrange for its sale. There's also
provision in here that requires the
director to adopt rules and regulations.
Um that would be open to everybody,
including city council, to see and weigh
in on for the sale of personal property,
which is very different than real
estate, which real estate the provisions
here model your existing ordinance.
Okay. Thank you. No, that's helpful. um
that that context kind of more answers
uh my question on that. Um and as of
right now, I don't I don't really have
much else. So, okay,
Councilman Ammed.
Uh thank you. Uh my only question is um
kind of a process question as it relates
to budgets. um with the charter and with
adopting the new admin code. Um
is there something that would prevent us
or would it be wise to put things in the
admin code for future budgets? Like like
for example, if council wanted to, you
know, make it a requirement that a
certain amount is in the critical
repairs program each year. I mean
technically that would have to be
adopted and approved by each council for
each subsequent budget moving forward or
with the new charter can we you know in
the admin code put certain budget
allocations for future budgets if that
makes sense.
I I understand the question. Um what I
would say is I mean I don't have the
case law to support it but I think the
answer is generally no. as a
municipality, you have to allocate
annually, and anything not listed isn't
allocated and appropriated. Um, and so I
think you would be uh potentially
violating the Pennsylvania Constitution.
Um, if you did that, um, the reality is
it means that you're paying attention
annually to that specific line item. Um,
if it's counsel's ultimately council's
approval of the budget while the mayor
presents it, it's council's budget. So,
if council wanted didn't like the
appropriation that was being suggested
by the mayor, uh it could change it
during that process.
That doesn't mean that you can't um you
know be working in advance. Keep in mind
the budget process now starts
considerably earlier, right? So, we're
starting here in uh months in advance
and council should be having an is is
going to be getting quarterly reports
and monthly statements, but quarterly
reports in particular. If these are
things that that council is interested
in having in the upcoming budget, that's
a conversation that should be had with
the director of administrative services
as early as possible each year.
Yeah. Yeah. And I guess like if it was
like kind of like you know our reserve
funds needs to be at x% of the budget or
if we are there's many different
examples but that's what I was wondering
kind of in like a good financial
management way. Is there are can are we
able to do that in like a one shot
through the code or does it have to be
annual allocations?
Well, you always have to do annual
annual allocations. That being said, the
admin code has set up a whole series of
financial policies um financial
guidelines. The policies ultimately will
have to come back to you as they're
completed that would have sort of target
numbers for say debt service, target
numbers for fund balances, etc. Um
but you still have to go through the
appropriate allocation and appropriation
process on an annual basis. And and I
would just add that um in contra in
contrast to the home rule charter which
cannot be chained changed the admin code
can also be changed on a regular basis
and and a and a budget is um my
understanding has always been that a
budget is an annual allocation and that
you cannot make commitments for future
budget years but you can have policy
guidance to direct the allocation or um
the the capital or capital reserves or
whatever policy statement there is, but
annually you would still need to have
that budget allocation. And because it's
an annual allocation, just the same um
there there's obviously policy that is
embedded into a budget at the same time.
Uh you can change the admin code. So
even if you're trying to prioritize it
through the admin code, the the place
where it is going to affectuate the most
changes actually in the budget.
Yeah. And that's that was that was
really um the basis of my question was
kind of from like the policy s side and
like can we set policies that would
affect future budgets? Yeah. And I think
the answer there is really you can't you
can't directly
control the subsequent budget. You can
only control the current one. Um that
being said, you want to put policies in
place that keep it that that direct the
administration on how to administer the
budget ordinance on an annual basis.
Right? So keep in mind again council
sets the legislation and the
administration effectuates that
legislation. So policy is helping them
to make decisions some of which require
your approval. So certain changes in the
budget during a year would require your
approval. certain um expenditures that
are not al that are not uh within budget
lines would require council's approval.
But even within ones that are allowed
within the budget, there can be
decisions to be made about the best way
to to handle it. And that guides not
only the current practice, but then the
drafting of the next year's budget. And
there you go. And uh just my like my
final piece of kind of where like my
thought process was going on this. Um
you know there's been a lot of talks
about tax exemption.
You know there's there's been a lot of
uh talks about you know tax exemptions
for low-inccome earners. Um, and a
question that did come in to my mind
was, you know, through the admin code,
would we be able to exempt any future
increases to earned income tax for
lowincome earners? Um, written in the
admin code. Um, I understand
retroactively we may not be able to do
that for any future
um, increases in our income tax. Would
that have to be done on a year-to-year
budget or would we be able to put in the
admin code that any future increases
would not affect those making under
12,000?
Uh, the exemption has to be done by
ordinance. Um, and it will have to be
done on an annual basis. Every tax is
adopted annually. So, you can't
prescribe it going forward.
That that's concludes my questions.
Thank you,
councelor Bake. I I think we have
consensus to move this section
okay
forward. Um
that's what I'm hearing. Councilors, are
there any other discussion points for
the sections that we are reviewing for
this meeting?
And I thank you for your questions and
suggestions. I think we'll have
more in the next section. So, okay. All
right. Um, so thank you very much,
counselors. Thank you, Mr. Handworker.
Um, that will move us into our public
comment period for this agenda. Uh,
public comment is open to members of the
public. I would ask that if you have
public comment that you step up step up
to the microphone that's over there so
you can be heard in the room. Comments
are limited to three minutes per
speaker. Please begin with your name and
block of residence for our meeting
record. If you have any comments, now is
the time.
You may need to turn that microphone on.
Thank you.
Tony Dastra, 700 block New Holland
Avenue.
A variety of minor concerns, but I'll
just start with uh my biggest concern,
which is I actually think article five
of the admin code asserts the authority
of the ethics commission. um that was
expressly written under article 12. I do
understand the logic. Um but I think the
ethics commission needs to have their
input on that. Uh and it needs to be
part of the ethics code, not the
administrative code.
Um
Mr. Dasher, just a quick response to
that.
Mr. Hburger, can you wait until Mr.
Dastra has concluded his three minutes?
Thank you.
So yeah, uh but to some earlier points
made by people up on the day or rather
at the table, um the charter is the
Bible and let me actually look up
something in my three minutes.
I could be wrong, but I do believe that
uh the charter can be amended through
referendums so long as it's not
affecting the government structure. Uh
some of my other concerns to these
proposed administrative code changes uh
I think are appropriate there through
that mechanism. Uh I think there are
some ways the city's opening itself up
to legal challenges between the powers
of uh of itself frankly uh because
there's language not included in the
charter that the administrative code
puts different prescriptions onto. So um
yeah I I think a lot of this does make
sense. I think there's a lot of logic
and reason, but I think the process
through which a lot of this is being
done isn't congruent without how it
needs to occur. Uh, so I'll save the
extra 45 seconds of my time and give it
back. Uh, thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Dastra.
Mr. Hannburger.
Got it.
Uh, article five deals with confidential
information as I indicated last month.
Um we have not yet drafted an ethics
code. Uh that is to be waited until the
ethics commission has its first meeting
and starts working makes recommendations
to council. Um again under the charter
the ethics commission does not draft the
ethics code rather it makes
recommendations to council. Uh those
will those those recommendations will
then be taken incorporated into a draft
which would be ultimately incorporated.
But the ethics code has not yet been
done.
So that larger section will be in the
next set of discussions. It will not um
because the ethics commission will not
have uh done all of its work yet. So
that will be sort of an ongoing
plugin as we move forward.
But it will be finished before we would
approve.
That's the goal.
The admin code. Okay. So it will be a
part of what this body votes to approve.
Yeah. Either way, the ethics code can be
separate or part of the admin code.
Either way, the ethics code has a
different time frame for adoption under
the admin code. Under the charter, the
ethics code has to be adopted within 12
months. the admin code within 18. So no
matter what this council has to approve
an ethics code um by the end of the
year. Um it is the hope that the logical
place for it is ultimately within the
admin code.
Um so the concept is to try and merge
the uh the recommendations of the ethics
uh commission into ethics code
provisions that will be inserted into
the admin code.
Thank you. I'm inclined to agree
counselors. I think we need to it's
important to have this process wrapped
up for in both cases the end of the year
despite the time frame being longer for
the admin code um before a new council
is seated before a new mayor is seated I
think it's extremely important so thank
you for that are there any additional
comments from the public this evening
right hearing none uh then we have
reached the conclusion of the agenda for
this evening I'll hear a motion to
adjurnn
Motion to adjurnn.
All in favor?